This this session is going to be more of
a case study. Uh so what we're going to
do is we're going to uh hear from uh
from Topo Pal uh who is uh who is a vice
president uh at Fidelity Investments um
uh of enterprise architecture and at
Fidelity that they've been you know
doing a little case study on this
individual or group who using Copilot um
and one of the things that we're going
to learn here is what works well what
are the limitations and and so forth but
case studies are always good in these
conferences so it gives me great
pleasure to introduce Typo on stage. So,
please give it up for
>> Typo. Thank you. All right. [music]
So, uh I'll be talking about a
particular use case that uh I was part
of at Fidelity Investments. Uh and then
we're going to talk about what that use
case was, what was done, what was good,
what was bad, what was the learning from
there. But before that uh I will kind of
first introduce myself formally and talk
about fidelity a little bit and then
show you certain disclaimers and then go
from there.
All right. Uh there are a few
disclaimers here. U it's a case study of
fidelity investments experience. Uh we
are not I am not endorsing any vendor or
any particular technology here. be just
presenting the uh use case and most of
the things that I say here are maybe all
are my opinions and my experience and
not necessarily Fidelity Investments or
any of its affiliates. So that's a set
of disclaimers
about Fidelity. I'm sure you all know
about Fidelity Investments, one of the
largest financial institutes in the
world. uh headquartered in Boston about
77,000 associates uh in all over the US
and many global sites there are 14 of
them in 11 countries uh total assets
under administration is $16.7 trillion
and total discretionary assets are $6.4
4 trillion. So it's huge. Uh and then
4.3 million daily average trades by
customers across uh across the world. So
that's kind of the scale that I'm
talking about. And of course, you know,
in big enterprises, especially on uh in
enterprises that are uh regulated, uh
things work in a different way than
normal startup or midsize companies that
are not so regulated would. So that's
about fidelity investments and the
reason I like fidelity investments is
because of these it's leading in
technology. There is vitality in my in
people's career and the most thing that
I like about is is very open to
diversity and inclusion and so I love
being there being as a developer being
as an architect being as an engineer in
general. So let's
talk about me currently um as I was
introduced uh vice president fidelity
architecture and engineering group there
are two things that I'm accountable for
one is software delivery domain
architecture strategy roadmap platform
functioning and then I also have
opensource program office previously I
was with capital one for 10 years uh
home depot for a little while quadrade
got acquired by newance and now
Microsoft uh I was with circuit city for
some long time and then before that I
was in academia I did my PhD in
semiconductor physics uh but that was a
completely different story how I landed
in software industry uh few years ago I
was fortunate enough to co-author this
book called investments unlimited this
is about automated governance with
devops in large enterprises and
financial institute Um and IT revolution
was uh gave us the opportunity to
publish this under their uh under their
umbrella. So that's about me.
Infidelity we have this hypothesis that
JAI coding assistance can accelerate
development streamline code reviews. You
just heard about that uh from Microsoft.
Enhance test coverage and support faster
delivery cycles. So in my talk I'm going
to kind of sort of prove the hypothesis
but before that I want to set the
context. My background is uh hands-on
keyboard developer. That's what I did
for most of my life. Even today uh I
have been with uh many software
engineering group for a long time. I can
code very well in Java. I can code in
Python. I can hack around with few other
languages but Java is my strong point.
Uh I have been with as as team lead uh I
have been with support uh groups uh
support lead. I logged into production I
broke production many times. uh it was
because of me that something bad
happened and every time that happened I
got promoted and that's how I'm here and
now I cannot quote that much uh that I
would like to and that's because I
actually can you know use my experience
in driving or leading teams or
instructing people to do the right thing
right away. So that is kind of my
background.
Now my use case as you have seen uh in
my in my current role I run open source
program office one of my teams run open
source program office for fidelity
enterprise
uh one thing that I care about in terms
of opensource governance is software
bill of material and uh I don't know how
many of you know Josh Garman he has been
the in the forefront of software bill of
material u and the necess necessity of
it. Uh he he introduced me to uh
software bill of material and hence
henceforth I'm going to talk about bomb
as software bill of material. He
introduced me to SBOM in around 2015.
Uh and it was it was kind of the eye
openening experience for me what he was
thinking about or talking about. And
during the last uh or few years ago in
in 2021 December when lock for shell
came about we all felt the need of
having an bomb uh in every company. Many
companies had that in some form of
fashion but not all. So this became one
of my uh target in my mind to have a
software bill of material to visualize
and analy analyze every use of
open-source software in the company in
all the applications in all the
repositories where they're running in
runtime environment the complete picture
of it. My point is that yes we talk
about is bomb in the context of security
but in my mind that is not only about
security it's about your software health
it's just like you buy a food package
and in the back of the package
everything is written down to the
details that you would like to know I
want to know that kind of detail for
every software that I build or I use or
run in my environment so it is not about
just security my goal is to achieve this
if you are building software, you need
to know your components. That's kind of
the basic goal. So that's my use case,
software bill of material use case. Now
over the last two and a half years, uh I
have a team that produced a complete
dependency graph and metadata of
internally built applications. is
essentially capturing dependency data
from repositories, artifact, runtime
environment and putting all these things
in a graph so that I can talk about a
particular library that I am interested
in and identify within seconds which
repository it is used in which artifact
it is embedded in, which Docker image it
is packaged in, and where it is running.
That's kind of the overall goal. Think
about lock for shell situation again.
Can I respond to a lock for shell
situation in the future within seconds
at least understanding what the impact
is? Now this team is an amazing team of
ter team of backend developers. They're
very good at Python and you know batch
kind of processing is essentially an ETL
job if you think about it. Collecting
data from multiple sources and putting
into the graph. Now what happened was um
as as they were building it people
across the enterprise were finding more
use of that data. So the this team was
kind of getting bogged down into
supplying report for all the people that
were asking for more data. Hey who uses
this particular library that we license
and how many applications are using it?
Who uses this software that is 10 years
old and we want to get rid of who get
rid of it? who who do you need to
contact? So that kind of reporting. So
what we thought is we'll produce a
dashboard that can have all these
features built in so that the users can
selfs serve. So that is the use case. So
we started with a so this
[clears throat] is a highle architecture
I just talked about from repository to
artifact to container images to runtime.
We gathered data and put it in a graph
and they are all connected via different
relationships and then we uh started
using NeoDash which comes with Neo forj
uh open source out of the box. It
basically connects to the graph database
and it has drag and drop almost
capabilities to visualize your graph and
query and all that. It's an open source
thing. Uh what we found was that [sighs]
it is good. It is free. It's ready to
go, ready to connect to Neo4j and do the
job. But I'll show you some of the
screenshots and and and it will
understand why it is not such a good
dashboard from user experience
perspective. Uh it actually directly
connects to the Neo 4G database. Some of
these response that comes up with such
as if you look at this particular screen
here, you can enter an application
number. Every big enterprise has an ID
for an application. So you put that
number and immediately it tells you some
details metadata about that
applications. How many libraries are
used in that application how many
repositories are in that particular
application their health in terms of
their software vulnerability and risk
and all that and some details. Now this
is all redacted out for good reason. I
don't want you to know all the details
that are behind. So all the XY
coordinates and some numbers have been
redacted on purpose but they have some
numbers shown on the neoash screen. This
is another view. You can actually put in
a library name and it will tell you how
many or which repositories are using
that particular library with many more
metadata. Um again some things have been
deducted out but overall we felt that
this experience is not good enough. it
cannot be scaled across the enterprise
uh because people will not love to use
that and when when people do not love to
use that they will come back to the team
asking for more reports. So we thought
that we need to somehow do something
about it and then as I said my
background was in Java as a major pro uh
programming languages and of course I
have worked with many RDBMS but Neo4j I
have nothing I have I don't know
anything about Neo forj and the quering
language cipher query I have no idea. So
I thought that maybe it's time for me to
learn cipher query and so that I can
experience some of the things that are
going on and find a solution from purely
from an architect perspective. So
this is what I have today as I said and
in my mind I needed this extra two
things a set of APIs and a nice usable
dashboard. the API of course for the
dashboard but also the use the the API
some of the APIs can be exposed to the
broad mass so that they can consume
there my first experiments were with
this with copilot I asked can I get
schema of my neoforj data and copilot
says yes you run this command and I took
that command and put it on neoforj
browser which is essentially a SQL
developer if you will and I got the
schema and then I said Okay, given that
schema, can you help me with some cipher
queries? I have some use cases. So,
copilot says, okay, give me the schema
and I'll give you the cipher query for
your queries. So, I put the schema in
and I asked based on this schema, can
you tell me this particular library is
used in how many repositories? So,
copilot gave me the uh query and I
pasted into the quote unquote SQL
developer. I got married. I'm like this
is quite a fun and I started making
complex uh use cases and it actually
produced all the right queries that I
can just took that took from there and
pasteed on the browser. So I started
thinking about it and when actually I
was pasting the queries in the Neoforj
browser I made sure of two things. One
I'm not in the production environment. I
didn't want to screw up any more
databases in my life. Number two, the
queries did not have delete, drop or
detach those dangerous commands. So
beyond that, I was safe to run those on
non-production environment and introduce
the things that I was looking for. So
then I started experimenting more. Um I
started talking about hey uh copilot can
you actually write a a single page
application uh showing these data points
and copilot did it in 1 hour and I was
very surprised and when I was getting
the success out of it then I said okay
let me just pause here and let me be a
little more bring in some discipline
into it. So this was my second
experiment. I actually closed the laptop
and wrote down everything that I needed
from this particular 2B set of APIs and
dashboard. These are the things that I
need. And then I typed that into
Copilot. I open my laptop, type that in
and I put in those requirements as well
as some very key nonfunctional
requirements that are very very
enterprise specific. My goal is not to
produce something that I cannot run in
an enterprise uh infrastructure. My goal
is to produce something and send it to
production in an enterprise from in a
financial in institute that is totally
regulated. So I fed those three things
in and I asked copilot read all this
apply all the knowledge that you have
about bomb across the whole internet all
the data set that you have been trained
on and write me a detailed
implementation plan detailed task list.
It took about 45 minutes to produce that
and I looked at that and I reviewed all
that in about one and a half a day. And
then I asked copilot what would it take
for a normal agile team let's say five
six developers and a scrum master and
and that group to implement this.
co-pilot thought for a few minutes and
gave me an estimate of 12 to 18 months
and I said that's not going to happen
[laughter] in a in a in a in a nobody's
going to build a dashboard instead of
API for nothing. So let me try. So next
5 days
uh I actually sat with co-pilot 5 days I
mean continuous 5 days that includes
nights uh I sat with co-pilot and went
through each and every task list using
many many many different uh models and
failing on the way and recovering from
the failure because I was learning uh
the whole process. So at the end of the
five day five days I had this react
fronted node typescript backend APIs
code for SSO integration as I talked
about uh enterprise form SSO is by
default uh needs to be on feature
toggles enterprise standard logging uh
end to end request tracing correlation
performance monitoring hooks unit and
end to end test sweet more than 80% code
coverage zero linting and code quality
issues, a docker pip file, a CI
pipeline, a partial deployment pipeline,
an architecture diagram, all in markdown
format. So this is the end result of
this 5 days of VIP coding and of course
there are few functional bugs. Now let
me show you what I got.
This is the new dashboard. Again things
are redacted out. There are few few
screenshots and if you catch me in the
in the after my talk I can show you the
real live uh application. So essentially
at a very high level it shows you
enterprise viewpoint your top technology
stacks your vulnerability chains your
license risk distribution
and in the license risk distribution it
can identify all the different licenses
the risk profile the distribution around
all the libraries and nice charts and
nice colors and nice font and nice
modern dashboard
bill of material registry which is this
particular product that we are talking
about if we enter that particular
application. It lists all the
dependencies that that particular
application has and with their
vulnerabilities, their other
dependencies, their transitive
dependencies, the license information,
recommended action and again this is
just presentation and API the data is
already there. So
another thing uh let's say lock 4J
happened I can have this library search
which says you know I type in lo forj it
shows up matches and then I can also
find let's say hey in the search result
match I had commons collection I can
select one and show usage the usage will
show all the repositories and artifacts
that this particular library is being
used in and I also have so that's the
usage report now I also have another
interesting thing the graph itself
copilot helped me actually build this
graph on the fly given an application it
can actually show me all the
repositories that are blue the red
hexagonal thing is actually the
application so essentially what we are
seeing here is that that particular
application has six repositories that
are the blue and for each repository it
has all the direct and indirect
dependencies in a graph form and you can
actually drag and drop So actually you
can separate them out and you can hover
over them to see their immediate
uh ages or immediate dependencies and
you can actually also see the transitive
dependencies.
Now at this point I wanted to know how
large this is this project because I had
no idea I didn't code a single line
right so I didn't know what what what is
there I just saw some API code and some
UI so I counted I mean I asked copilot
to count it this is the size of the
project 36,000 about 37,000 lines of
NodeJS backend and 30,000 lines of react
typescript and 270 source code file
yesterday I did another count and I saw
that API server has code base has grown
5%. The front end code base has grown
45%. So what I'm saying is that this is
the baseline after 5 days of Vive coding
and that's the kind of the size of the
project that came up uh copilot came up
with in 5 days. Now I was also
interested to know okay how good is this
project is you know beyond the number of
lines of code. So I asked copilot just
another model. Hey, look at this
particular repository and tell me how
good is this project. So this is exactly
cut, copy pasted from my co-pilot to my
slide. It says this particular project
needs senior plus developer skill with
full stack expertise with enterprise
software experience security security
domain knowledge and the bottom line is
this is the kind of project that gives
you the inter gets you interviews at fan
companies and demonstrate that you are
you can architect and build production
grade enterprise software and definitely
brag about it. So here I am bragging
about it and I have not written a single
line of code. Now you might ask that how
confident I am that without writing a
single line of code I am ready to ship
this code to the production and my point
is that that
I did not know when I started but after
5 days I actually know cipher queries
because copilot taught me I actually can
read TypeScript I actually know the
structure I actually can now code in
Typescript because that's what I
happened in this five days that with the
V coding going on. It actually taught me
the things that I did not know. This is
just amazing. Right now, my learning as
a developer, you all know this stuff. Do
not 100% trust your AI coaching agent.
They will lie to you. Use all the
scanners, splinters, and all that. I'm
going to quickly skip to the slide which
is more important for me as an architect
architecture lead. What are the things
that I worry about? The what I worry
about is this this amazing speed that
the jai coding agents are are going to
produce will actually collapse or create
back pressure on our rest of the
software delivery process. Think about
agile. Agile created a back pressure in
our dev and ops process. That's why we
have dev ops. This is many many many
magnitudes more. Think about getting one
feature done in one sprint to 10
features done in one day. Think about
the process that needs to be tuned up to
handle this pressure. How to do that? I
don't know. I'm still learning. So
that's why I'm showing up all in all
these conferences so that I can talk to
you and and learn about this. But the
change is here. We have to embrace the
change. It's not about can we use AI
geni coding agent. It's about how can we
use GI coding agent is the question.
This is one cautionary thing from my
side. Vive coding is very very
addictive. You can talk to my family.
They will tell you about it. Um so I'm
not going to lie. Um help. I'm looking
for these. If you have any any answers
to these, please come and talk to me.
Love to chat. I have 2 minutes and 20
seconds. I'm ready for questions. Thank
you.
[applause]
>> Thank you very much. Any questions in
the room?
and straight away.
>> How long did it take you after that to
register in the internal system ID and
run this in production? So this thing is
in production for last two months and it
is being totally managed by a team of
developers
that have no idea just like me how the
TypeScript works or how the TypeScript
API works or the UI. They now know and
they are maintaining the product. As I
said, 40% uh code growth over the last
one month all by co-pilot.
>> Hi, thank you for the talk here.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh what can you say about the reliance
on AI systems to build solutions that
you ultimately try to push to prod?
>> So this is in production but I
understand your question.
Let me ask myself this question. Am I
ready to use jai coding agents to write
software that handles money? Not yet. Am
I ready to actually offload some of
these task that big enterprises have
even small to medium this this no risk
applications like bomb dashboard right
these are internal tools. Am I ready to
offload those task to AI copilot 100%.
>> What does the clock say? 30 seconds or
so on the clock
>> 51 seconds. It's 51 seconds then,
>> right?
>> 49 48.
>> Okay. Okay. Okay. So, uh, Sbombs and,
um, vibe. So, do you foresee like in
your sbomb to say like a vibe level um
like an attribution of confidence that
the developer understands the component
they've written.
>> We are looking at it because one of the
things as an open source program office
owner I have in my mind is that it's not
only me writing VIP coding and
developing software. is the rest of the
open source world and who is keeping
track of all the security vulnerability
intentional versus and unintentional
things. So what am I consuming that I
cannot now track as fast as they are
being produced. So that is one of the
risk that we are thinking about how to
capture those kind of things. U I saw
some of the tools here that can probably
help and some of them are good open
source. So it's all good from now
onwards.
>> What a what a sentiment to finish on.
Thank you very much. Give it up to
[music]